Tengxiang Zhang

I am an Associate Research Scientist at the Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences. My research interests include: 1) Novel sensing and interaction techniques; 2) Tag-aided wireless spatial computing; 3) Semantic-based interaction abstraction theory and application.

EDUCATION

2016-2019	PhD, Human Computer Interaction, Computer Science	
	Tsinghua University, China	Advisor: Prof. Yuanchun Shi
2011-2013	MSc, Electromagnetics, Electrical Engineering	
	The University of Texas at Austin, USA	Advisor: Prof. Andrea Alu
2007-2011	BSc, Chien-Shiung Wu Honors College/Electrical Engineering	
	Southeast University, China	Research supervisor: Prof. Tiejun Cui

PUBLICATIONS

- **2022** [J.8] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Zitong Lan, Chenren Xu, Yanrong Li, and Yiqiang Chen. 2022. BLEselect: Gestural IoT Device Selection via Bluetooth Angle of Arrival Estimation from Smart Glasses. 2022. IMWUT. 6, 4. (accepted)
 - [O.6] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yinshuai Zhang, Xin Jiang, Xuhai Xu, Anind K Dey, and Yiqiang Chen. 2022. BoldMove: Enabling IoT Device Control on Ubiquitous Touch Interfaces by Semantic Mapping and Sequential Selection. In Extended Abstracts of the CHI 2022, 7.
 - [J.7] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Zi Qian, HsuanWei Fan, Jie Ren, Yuntao Wang, Yuanchun Shi. Easily-add Battery-free Wireless Sensors to Everyday Objects: A System Implementation and Usability Study. *CCF Transactions on Pervasive Computing and Interaction*.
- 2021 [O.5] Xin Zeng, Xinyi Yang, Tengxiang Zhang, Yukang Yan, Yiqiang Chen. ScreenJump: An AR-facilitated User-centric Interaction System for Fine-grained Resource Manipulation Across Displays. CHI 2021 Workshop on User Experience for Multi-Device Ecosystems: Challenges and Opportunities.
 - [J.6] Yingwei Zhang, Yiqiang Chen, Hanchao Yu, Zeping Lv, Xiaodong Yang, Chunyu Hu, **Tengxiang Zhang**. What Can "Drag & Drop" Tell? Detecting Mild Cognitive Impairment by Hand Motor Function Assessment under Dual-Task Paradigm. *International Journal of Human-Computer Studies* 145:102547.
- **2020** [C.3] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yinshuai Zhang, Ke Sun, Yuntao Wang, and Yiqiang Chen. 2020. ThermalRing: Gesture and Tag Inputs Enabled by a Thermal Imaging Smart Ring. In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20), 1–13.
 - [C.2] Yuntao Wang, Zichao (Tyson) Chen, Hanchuan Li, Zhengyi Cao, Huiyi Luo, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Ke Ou, John Raiti, Chun Yu, Shwetak Patel, and Yuanchun Shi. 2020. MoveVR: Enabling Multiform Force Feedback in Virtual Reality using Household Cleaning Robot. *In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20)*, 1–12.

- [O.4] **Tengxiang Zhang** and Steve Hodges. New Opportunities for Sustainable Interaction using Backscatter Sensors. *Workshop on self-powered sustainable interfaces and interactions (SelfSustainableCHI 2020)*
- **2019** [J.5] **Tengxiang Zhang,** Xin Yi, Ruolin Wang, Jiayuan Gao, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu, Simin Li, Yuanchun Shi. Facilitating Temporal Synchronous Target Selection through User Behavior Modeling. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.*, 2,4:159.
 - [J.4] Yuntao Wang, Jianyu Zhou, Hanchuan Li, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Minxuan Gao, Zhuolin Cheng, Chun Yu, Shwetak Patel, and Yuanchun Shi. FlexTouch: Enabling Large-Scale Interaction Sensing Beyond Touchscreens Using Flexible and Conductive Materials. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.*, 3,3:109.
 - [O.3] Jianfei Shen, **Tengxiang Zhang**, and Yiqiang Chen. Tap2Pair: Associating Wireless Devices with Tapping. *Adjunct Proceedings of UbiComp/ISWC '19*, *Pages 346-349*.
- **2018** [J.3] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Ruolin Wang, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu, Yiqin Lu, and Yuanchun Shi. 2018. Tap-to-Pair: Associating Wireless Devices with Synchronous Tapping. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 2, 4: 201.
 - [O.2] **Tengxiang Zhang.** 2018. Toward Pervasive Interaction: Empowering and Enriching Interactions on Resource-constrained Devices. *Adjunct Proceedings of UbiComp/ISWC '18*, Pages 504-509.
 - [O.1] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Chun Yu, Yuntao Wang, Nicholas Becker, and Yuanchun Shi. 2018. TOUCHPOWER: Interaction-based Power Transfer for Power-as-needed Devices. *GetMobile: Mobile Comp. and Comm.* 22, 2: 27–31. (Invited Highlights)
- **2017** [J.2] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Chun Yu, Yuntao Wang, Nicholas Becker, and Yuanchun Shi. 2017. TouchPower: Interaction-based Power Transfer for Power-as-needed Devices. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 1, 3: 121:1–121:20. (*Discussion Paper*)
 - [C.1] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Nicholas Becker, Yuntao Wang, Yuan Zhou, and Yuanchun Shi. 2017. BitID: Easily Add Battery-Free Wireless Sensors to Everyday Objects. *In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Smart Computing (SMARTCOMP)*, 1–8. (Best Paper Runner-up)
- 2013 [J.1] Huifeng Ma, Bengeng Cai, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Yan Yang, Weixiang Jiang, and Tiejun Cui. 2013. Three-Dimensional Gradient-Index Materials and Their Applications in Microwave Lens Antennas. *IEEE Transactions on Antennas and Propagation* 61, 5: 2561–2569.

PATENTS

- **2022** [P.11] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Yanrong Li ,Yiqiang Chen. Smart Glasses-based Facial Action Unit Detection Method and Apparatus *(pending)*
 - [P.10] Tengxiang Zhang, Zitong Lan, Yanrong Li, Yiqiang Chen. A Device Selection

- System and Method: CN 202211410562.4 (pending)
- [P.9] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen. An AR Device Felicitated Multi-Device Interaction System and Method: CN 202211490160.X (pending)
- **2021** [P.8] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen. A Semantic-based Device Association Method: CN 202110359565.9 *(pending)*
- **2020** [P.7] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen. A Smart Ring Based Gesture Recognition Method and System: CN 202010411317.X
 - [P.6] Tengxiang Zhang, Jiayuan Gao, Yiqiang Chen. Apparatus and Method for Cognitive Load Analysis Based on Near-infrared Imaging of Subcutaneous Veins: CN 202010459503.0
 - [P.5] Tengxiang Zhang, Jiayuan Gao, Yiqiang Chen. A Movement Symmetry Based Smart Prosthesis Control Method and System: CN 202010425034.0
- **2018** [P.4] Yuanchun Shi, Yinshuai Zhang, **Tengxiang Zhang**. One type of Smart Ring: CN 201821371671.9
 - [P.3] Yuanchun Shi, Yinshuai Zhang, **Tengxiang Zhang.** Smart Ring: CN 201821371641.8
 - [P.2] Yuanchun Shi, Tengxiang Zhang, Xin Yi, Yuntao Wang and Chun Yu. Pairing method and wireless device for pairing using wireless signals. International Patent No. PCT/CN2018/094468.
 - [P.1] Yuanchun Shi, Tengxiang Zhang, Xin Yi, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu. An association method and apparatus to pair devices based on wireless signals: CN 201810723952.4

GRANTS

- **2022** [I.5] **Principle Investigator:** Research on Pervasive Touch Interface and Interaction Design for IoT Device Control (300K CNY). NSFC Fund for Young Scholars.
- **2021** [I.4] **Principle Investigator:** Ultra-low-power Bluetooth-compatible Ubiquitous Touch Interface (20K CNY). Open project, Beijing Key Laboratory of Mobile Computing and Pervasive Device.
- **2020** [I.3] **Principle Executing Investigator:** A Movement Symmetry Based Smart Prosthesis Control Method (650K CNY). ICT, CAS Innovation Fund.
 - [I.2] **Co-Principle Investigator:** Resources Cross-modality Association and Matching Techniques (2.28 Million CNY), sub-project of Key Technologies for Modern Service Resource Management, National Key Research and Development Plan.
 - [I.1] **Co-investigator:** Hearing Aid Automatic Fitting Models (270K CNY), Key Technologies of Proactive Health and Aging Population, National Key Research and Development Plan.

HONORS AND AWARDS

2019	Graduate with Honor (CS), Tsinghua University, China	
2018	Finalist, Global Innovation Competition'18	
2017	Best Paper Runner-up, SMARTCOMP'17	
2017	Discussion Paper, UbiComp'17	

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2021- Associate Research Scientist, Institute of Computing Technology,

Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China

2019-2021 Assistant Research Scientist, Institute of Computing Technology,

Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China

• Conduct research on pervasive sensing and interactive systems and pervasive interaction techniques

Published papers on top-tier journals and conferences like CHI and IMWUT

 Granted research funds ~3 million CNY with 2 National Key Research and Development Plan funds

2015-2016 RF Engineer/Product Manager, Tomoon Technology, Beijing, China

Smartwatch and Bluetooth tracker antenna design

• Bluetooth tracker product definition, project management, field deployment

2013-2015 Product and Test Engineer, Silicon Labs, Austin, Texas, USA

• IoT MCU chips (e.g. Sub-GHz, ZigBee) RF calibration and test

• Test program (C/Perl) development, hardware design and layout

Developed on-chip test program that saved over 30% test time for EM357

SERVICES

Committee Member SIGCHI Sustainability Committee

CCF HCI Technical Program Committee CCF Ubicomp Technical Program Committee

Review CHI'20'21'22, IMWUT'21'22, UIST'20, MobileHCI'20, ISS'20,

IUI'20, TEI'20, EICS'19, TEI'21 WIP Program Committee

Volunteer ACM UBICOMP/ISWC 2018, Singapore;

The 4th UN World Urban Forum 2008, Nanjing, China

Academic Speaker Microsoft Research (Redmond)

GIX ACSP (Access Computing Summer Program) 2020

Mentor GIX ACSP '21'22, GIX 2019 Winter Camp

Chair HHME (largest conference for HCI and ubicomp in China) 2022 Tutorial

STUDENT SUPERVISION AND MENTORSHIP

Xin Zeng UCAS Ph.D (CS). Co-supervising with Prof. Yiqiang Chen Jiayuan Gao UCAS Ph.D (CS). Co-supervising with Prof. Yiqiang Chen Yanrong Li UCAS Master (CS). Co-supervising with Prof. Yiqiang Chen

Xiaoyu Wang Peking University Undergraduate (CS)
Zhengtai Gou Tsinghua Undergraduate (Automation)

*Zitong Lan SEU Undergraduate (CS)

*Xinran Chen UESTC Undergraduate (CS)

*Yaobin Su University of Copenhagen Master (CS)

*Xinyi Yang BJTU Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at CUHK

*Jiayin Wang Tsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Tsinghua (CS)

*Simin Li Beihang Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Georgia Tech (CS)

*Zi Qian
Tsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at U of Toronto (CS)
*Hsuan-Wei Fan
Tsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Cornell Tech (CS)
*Hanwei Wang
Tsinghua Undergraduate (Physics); Now Ph.D at UIUC (EE)

* Alumni

SKILLS

Programming languages: Python, C, C++, C#, Java, Matlab

Prototyping: Arduino, Processing, Altium, 3D printing

Software: Matlab, CST, Keras, Scikit-learn

Hardware: Signal generator, Vector network analyzer, Spectrum analyzer